There are lots of experiences that every dentist runs into that makes the day very hard.
Some of the complications that we run into could be something as simple as just not getting the patient adequately numb.
That certainly causes distress to the patient but also to the dentist.
There have been many times where the patient comes in with such a big infection or they're just a complicated patient and it is very difficult to get them numb.
That is certainly one problem we encounter from time to time.
Certainly because we have to take a lot of impressions on teeth or molds.
Some people have real problems with things in their mouth so you can kind of stimulate this gag reflex.
So that can be difficult where you have a patient that has a really bad gag reflex that you can't get a very good impression on.
That's another complication.
Another one that we run into from time to time is again if someone presents for an extraction and they want to get a tooth taken out and it is very badly broken.
We know that it is probably going to be a little more uncomfortable for the patient and certainly more difficult from our standpoint to get it out.
So it is just not as simple as going in and basically removing the tooth but sometimes it involves you know a little more gory detail to do things to basically remove the tooth.
Basically it all goes back to being able to relate and being empathetic with the patient provided that you are listening to the patient and you are kind of understanding their concerns and you are kind of talking through this.
It is more about kind of letting them know that you are on their side and you guys are a team and working together to kind of get to a common good.
So most of the problems we encounter are usually resolved with just talking with the patient in a soft spoken way and an empathetic manner so that the patient knows that you can understand what they are going through.
You are trying to help them get through it.